# Noel Moreno Lemus, Ph.D.

Panama



nmlemus@gmail.com



+50763994214



linkedin.com/in/nmlemus

# **Summary**

Data Science Professional with 20 years of experience working in different industry domains like:

- Life Sciences
- Oil & Gas
- BioTech (Drug Design, Bioinformatics, Clinical Trials)
- Advertising
- Retail
- Energy
- Logistic
- eCommerce
- IoT
- Software Development in General

Solid background in Mathematics, Probability, Statistics, Programming, Machine Learning, deep learning, communication skills, and business acumen. I also have more than 15 years of experience in people management.

I am a passionate learner who is always looking for a new challenge.

# **Experience**



# 🚾 Senior Data Scientist

Procter & Gamble

May 2022 - Present (9 months)

Responsible for end-to-end analytic leadership of Data Science projects including algorithm performance and effectiveness. Also responsible for building advanced analytic (ML/Al/Optimization) algorithms within a Data Science program and working with Business Partners and Friends of Data Science to insert algorithms into business processes and activate them directly with the business.



#### 🚾 Data Scientist

Procter & Gamble

Sep 2019 - May 2022 (2 years 9 months)

Responsible for building advanced analytic (ML/Al/Optimization) algorithms within a Data Science program and working with Business Partners and Friends of Data Science to insert algorithms into business processes and activate them directly with the business.

#### → Postdoctoral Researcher

Universidade Federal Fluminense

Aug 2018 - May 2019 (10 months)

Research Proposal: Computational modeling and simulation of epidemic infectious diseases

- Conducted independent research and development to attain short and long-term objectives.
- Wrote and published peer-reviewed articles concerning findings and highlighted possible applications for findings.
- Contributed to and actively participated in research conception, design and execution to address defined problems.
- Collaborated with multidisciplinary team members to accomplish the research goals of the project.
- Leveraged interpersonal and communication skills to mentor Ph.D., graduate, and undergraduate students.



#### Scientific Researcher

**Dell EMC** 

Feb 2014 - Aug 2015 (1 year 7 months)

Research Project: Visualization and Analysis for Seismic Interpretation

- Automatically identifying possible faults in large seismic datasets.
- An exemplary method comprises obtaining the seismic data; calculating a coherence cube of the seismic data; performing the following steps for a plurality of two-dimensional seismic sections of the coherence cube: (i) applying a threshold to the coherence cube to obtain a binary image representation comprising continuities; (ii) identifying edges of continuity areas in the binary image representation to identify changes in the continuities as fault point candidates; (iii) identifying fault points in the obtained seismic data based on a fault confidence value indicating a likelihood that a given point is part of a fault; (iv) creating one or more fault segments from the identified fault points; and (v) joining fault segments into fault lines using geological and/or geometrical constraints; and generating three-dimensional fault surfaces from the fault lines in the plurality of two-dimensional seismic sections
- The exemplary automatic fault detection method can be parallelized.

# **Assistant Professor**

Universidad Agraria de La Habana (UNAH) "Fructuoso Rodríguez Pérez"

Sep 2011 - Aug 2012 (1 year)

Disciplines:

- Linear Algebra
- Numerical Methods

### Objectives:

- Used a variety of learning modalities and support materials to facilitate the learning process and accentuate presentations.
- Collaborated with colleagues on curriculum revision, evaluation of course syllabi and lesson plans for Linear Algebra and Numerical Methods curriculum.
- Helped struggling students by providing support outside of classrooms and consistently checking in on progress.
- Mentored students and communicated internship and employment opportunities.
- Contributed to campus activities to promote a positive university image.

# UCI

### Head of the Bioinformatic R&D Group

Universidad de las Ciencias Informáticas

Sep 2004 - Aug 2010 (6 years)

As a Head of the Bioinformatics Research Group, I organized the work of more than 30 professionals from different areas as Biochemistry, Biology, Mathematics, Computer Science, and Information Technologies; and 200+ students between 3er and 5th of the Information Science Engineers course. The work was organized into 9 Research & Developed projects that tried to solve problems for the Research Centers of the Scientific Pole of the West of Havana, Cuba. Some of the main projects were:

- BioSyS: Biologic System Simulator
- J-IMMSIM: Immune System Simulator
- Grato: Computer-Aided Drug Design Framework
- LIMS: Laboratory Information Management System for the CIGB, Cuba.
- T-arenal: Platform of Distributed Tasks
- BioNova: Bioinformatic Linux Distribution
- Farmaco-kinetic web App

#### Additionally I organizes:

- Scientific seminars and conferences
- Advanced and postgraduate courses
- Coordinate the program of Master in Bioinformatics, which took place in two editions 2005-2007 and 2008-2010.
- Guarantee the quality of the complete flow of software development, from the definition of the requirements to the quality tests of the software, its implementation, and its future maintenance and improvement.

#### Main results:

- The Bioinformatics Research Group was the best research group of the University in 2007, 2008 and 2009
- The Software BioSyS and T-arenal were registered in the Cuban Office of Intellectual Property
- The algorithms and software developed by the group were used by the Research Centers of the Scientific Pole of the West of Havana to conduct its investigations.

# Academic Advisor

Universidad de las Ciencias Informáticas

Sep 2004 - Aug 2010 (6 years)

Master Degree Dissertations:

- 1. Yudelkis Abad: "Software para la estimacion de parametros y analisis de sensibilidad en SED". 2010
- 2. Yunet Gonzalez Mulet. "Metodología para el análisis de estabilidad de Sistema de Ecuaciones Diferenciales n-dimensionales". 2010

#### Engineering Degree:

- 1. Indira Rodriguez: "Implementacion del GROMACS en ambiente distribuido. 2011.
- 2. Katia Manchon: BioG: desarrollo de un módulo de simulación de sistemas dinámicos. 2009.
- 3. Yanet Fajardo. BioSyS: análisis de series temporales mediante técnicas de clustering. 2009.
- 4. Jorge Diaz. BioSyS: adición de nuevos métodos de simulación y utilización e integración del asistente matemático Octave, 2009
- 5. Yilian Rodriguez. BioSyS: Implementación del Módulo de Análisis.. 2008.

- 6. Adriel Acosta. Simulador del Sistema Inmune J-ImmSim, 2008
- 7. Alfredo Martinez. BioSyS: Módulo de Modelación Gráfica de Sistemas Biológicos, 2008
- 8. Mabel Navarro. BioSyS: Implementación del Módulo de Simulación. 2008
- 9. Niurka Martinez Duran. Portal Web de Servicios Bioinformáticos, 2008
- 10. Roberto Maldonado. Estimación de Parámetros en SED, 2008
- 11. Diana del Fresno. Aplicación Web para Estudios Farmacocinéticos, 2007
- 12. Yeniley Matos. Simulador para el Sistema Inmune. 2007
- 13. Mabelis Padron. Distribución de Linux específica para Bioinformática. 2007
- 14. Yunet Gonzalez. Módulo de Simulación y Análisis para BioSyS, 2007
- 15. Ileana Centelles. Editor de Ecuaciones Diferenciales para BioSyS, 2007
- 16. Anthony Sotolongo. Herramienta para la Modelación de Sistemas Biológicos. 2006
- 17. Celia Garcés. Sistema automatizado para el control de la calidad en el laboratorio clínico. 2005
- 18. Yaima Fiallo. Sistema Automatizado para el Registro Cubano de Discapacitados. 2005
- 19. Danay Rodriguez. Sistema para el Registro Cubano de Malformaciones Congénitas. 2005
- 20. Karel Osorio. Plataforma para el Desarrollo de la Biología de Sistemas, 2004

# Project Manager: BioSyS (Biological System Simulator)

Universidad de las Ciencias Informáticas

Sep 2003 - Aug 2010 (7 years)

- Developed and initiated projects, managed costs, and monitored performance.
- Adhered to industry practices, company standards, and safety protocols in work.
- Completed assignments ahead of the deadline.
- Assisted in level-loading project capacity and made proactive decisions around process improvements to the development cycle.
- Modeled management and organizational skills and multi-tasked and prioritized in a deadline-driven environment.
- Developed project timelines for product lines from kickoff through production and online content development based on marketplace requirements.
- Verified quality of deliverables and conformance to specifications before submitting to clients.
- Tracked project and team member performance closely to quickly intervene in mistakes or delays.
- Recruited and oversaw personnel to achieve performance and quality targets.
- Built successful project plans covering objectives, resources, and staffing to meet schedules.
- Scheduled and facilitated meetings between project stakeholders to discuss deliverables, schedules and conflicts.

### Assistant Professor

Universidad de las Ciencias Informáticas

Sep 2002 - Jan 2010 (7 years 5 months)

Disciplines:

- Linear Algebra
- Discrete Mathematics
- Mathematical Models in Biology
- Introduction to Bioinformatics
- Probabilities and Statistics
- Numerical Methods
- GNU/Linux

# Objectives:

- Used a variety of learning modalities and support materials to facilitate the learning process and accentuate presentations.
- Took attendance, graded assignments, and maintained student records to assist teachers with administrative tasks and maintain smooth daily operations.
- Collaborated with colleagues on curriculum revision, evaluation of course syllabi, and lesson plans.
- Helped struggling students by providing support outside of classrooms and consistently checking in on progress.
- Proctored exams and provided remediation for learning improvement goals.
- Created materials and exercises to illustrate the application of course concepts.
- Facilitated academic and community collaborations to increase the number of community-engaged research proposal submissions to extramural funders.
- Mentored students and communicated internship and employment opportunities.
- Contributed to campus activities to promote a positive university image.
- Evaluated and supervised student activities and performance levels to provide reports on academic progress.
- Applied innovative teaching methods to encourage student learning objectives.

# **Education**



# National Laboratory of Scientific Computing

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computational Modeling

2013 - 2018

The Ph.D. Program in Computational Modeling aims at providing a multidisciplinary advanced education in Computer Sciences, Applied Mathematics and Modeling to Graduates in Mathematics, Physics, Chemistry, Engineering, Computer Science, Biology, Economics or other related areas.

Dissertation: Generalized lambda distribution for uncertainty quantification of large-scale Spatio-temporal models.



# Institute of Technologies And Applied Sciences (InsTEC)

Master's degree, Bioinformatics

2005 - 2007

The field of Bioinformatics is an area of study that involves several fields, including computer science, molecular biology, genetics, and statistics. Bioinformatics is devoted to the development of theoretical and computational models and technologies for the solution of problems based on molecular data. In general, it involves the use of information technologies for the management of biological and genetic information, namely, to collect, store, analyze, and integrate data.

The main goals of Bioinformatics are:

- to manage data in such a way that it allows easy access to the existing information and to submit new entries as they are produced;
- to develop technological tools that help analyze biological data;
- and to use these tools to analyze the data and interpret the results from a biological perspective.



# Institute of Nuclear Sciences And Technology (ISCTN)

Bachelor's degree, Radiochemistry

1997 - 2002

Radiochemistry is the chemistry of radioactive materials; it involves study of chemical transformations of radioactive substances, dealing with actinides and transuranium elements, development of physicochemical principles of handling radioactive waste from nuclear power engineering, solving radioecology problems, developing methods for manufacturing sources of radioactive emissions, and separation of radioactive isotopes.

# IPVCE Federico Engels

High School, High School/Secondary Diplomas and Certificates 1993 - 1996

# **Licenses & Certifications**

- Scrum Fundamentals Certified (SFC) SCRUMstudy Accreditation Body for Scrum and Agile
  893542
- Introduction to TensorFlow Coursera
  Z27R8X4CDEN7
- Launching into Machine Learning Coursera
  3U7RHP96R9WE
- How Google does Machine Learning Coursera
  MJBAB8LGLR7G
- Google Cloud Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals Coursera
  Z5LTMZZT5ZJV
- Art and Science of Machine Learning Coursera
  T3CG45DZK4LF
- Launch & Learn: BigQuery Game Google Cloud Skills Boost 1108163
- Google Cloud Essentials Google Cloud Skills Boost 1108247

# **Skills**

Project Management • Research • Statistics • Leadership • Google Cloud Platform (GCP) • Team Leadership • Data Science • Machine Learning • Mathematical Modeling • Big data